Flying Club Records, 1934-1954
Smith College Archives
Flying Club Records
1934-1954
Flying Club
RG 80 UUID:646f700a-bcf0-4140-806a-20fa318888c8
1 box (.5 linear ft.)
Smith College Archives Northampton, MA
Contains constitution, correspondence, flight training and financial records, photographs, publications, manuals and instructions.
In 1934, Mary Kimball, an avid aviator, founded the Smith College Flying Club so that she and other young women would have the opportunity to learn more about aviation and to participate in intercollegiate air meets and activities while at Smith. While the club attracted only twelve members at its founding, its membership increased and during its peak years, as many as forty young women could be seen attending lectures on flight theory and mechanics and participating in flying exercises and meets throughout New England. In 1950, however, Flying Club members were prohibited from competing in air meets due to a violation of college policy. While the club was allowed to continue its existence as long as members did not participate in competitions, membership declined and in 1954, the Flying Club was discontinued. The club was the first organization of its kind to be formed and supported by a women's college in the East.
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
All of the files are open to the public according to the regulations of the Smith College Archives.
History of the Collection
Search Terms
Flying Club (Smith College).; Smith College--Societies, etc.; Women air pilots--Massachusetts--Northampton.
Additional Information
Flying Club Books, Publications, Manuals, and Instructions
Boeing School of Aeronautics. "A Guide to Aeronautical Occupations." U.S.A.: Boeing School of Aeronautics, 1940.
Civil Aeronautics Authority. "Digest of the Civil Air Regulations for Student and Private Pilots." Washington: United States Government Printing Office, 1940.
Civil Air Patrol. "Organization Purpose Program Enlistment." Washington D.C.: United States Office of Civilian Defense, 1941.
Lyon, Thoburn C. "Practical Air Navigation." Washington: United States Government Printing Office, 1939.
Mahachek, Ross. Airplane Pilot's Manual. New York: G. P. Putnam's Sons, 1932.
Mingos, Howard. Flying for 1937. New York: Aeronautical Chamber of Commerce of America, Inc., 1936.
Reader's Digest. "A Pocket Reference Guide to Army-Navy-Air Corps Insignia." 1943
Sorenson, Frank E. "Essential Understandings for the Age of Flight." U.S.A.: State of Nebraska Department of Public Instruction, 1944.
Taylorcraft Aviation Corp. "America's Wings: Taylorcraft." Cleveland: Copifyer Lithogram Corp., 1941.
U.S. Army Air Forces, Office of Flying Safety. "I've Got Wings!" U.S.A.: U.S. Army Air Forces, Office of Flying Safety, n.d.
U.S. Civil Aeronautics Authority. "Primary Ground Study Manual." Washington: United States Government Printing Office, 1939.
United Air Lines. "S.V.E. Picturol Teacher's Manual." Chicago: Society for Visual Education, n.d.
Wheatley, William A. and Ray O. Mertes, ed. " Aviation Manual for Junior and Senior High Schools." Chicago: United Air Lines, n.d.
- General (1) 1934-1948 (Box 3013)
- General (2) Stars and Stripes and Springfield Union Articles (Originals) 1942-1945 (Box 3013)
- Constitution, first and revised undated (Box 3013)
- Correspondence 1939-1950 (Box 3013)
- Financial 1941-1943 (Box 3013)
- Flight Training 1939-1945 (Box 3013)
- Intercollegiate Flying Club 1935, undated (Box 3013)
- Membership 1936-1943 (Box 3013)
- Merger with Amherst Flying Club 1940 (Box 3013)
- Photographs 1939 (Box 3013)
- Photographs 1941-1945 (Box 3013)
- Photographs undated (Box 3013)
- Publications, Manuals, and Instructions (1) (Box 3013)
- Publications, Manuals, and Instructions (2), See list of publications. (Box 3013)